Finding Aid for the Margaret Ann Roth Photographs MS.3201
University of Tennessee Libraries, Special Collections
Margaret Ann Roth Photographs
1955 April 3-1958 November 26
MS.3201
University of Tennessee Libraries, Special Collections
2.0 Linear feet
This collection consists of photographs and corresponding negatives taken by Margaret Ann Roth. Some of the subjects depicted include football games at the University of Tennessee in the 1950s, various parts of the Smoky Mountains, and dams in various stages of construction in the East Tennessee area.
Roth, Margaret, (Margaret Ann), 1921-2004
Conditions Governing Access
Colletions are stored offsite, and a minimum of 24 hours is needed to retrieve these items for use. Researchers interested in consulting any of the collections are advised to contact Special Collections at special@utk.edu.
Acquisition Note
This collection is property of the University of Tennessee Libraries, Knoxville, Special Collections.
Biographical/Historical Note
No biographical information is available.
Scope and Contents Note
This collection consists of photographs and corresponding negatives taken by Margaret Ann Roth. Some of the subjects depicted include football games at the University of Tennessee in the 1950s, various parts of the Smoky Mountains, and dams in various stages of construction in the East Tennessee area.
The photographs documenting the construction of dams in East Tennessee contain images of Morgan Dam, Chilhowee Dam, Fort Loudon Dam, and Douglas Dam taken in 1956. Other engineering photographs include shots of the Southern Railway Crash that took place at Powell's Station in 1956 and the destruction of the Pratt Store following a fire in 1955.
The images documenting University of Tennessee football games include images of the UT-Georgia Tech game of 1955 November 6 (which ended in a tie with both teams scoring seven points), the UT-Georgia Tech game of 1957 November 9 (which UT won 21-7), the UT-Maryland game of 1956 October 7 (which UT won 34-7), and the UT-Kentucky game of 1958 November 22 (which UT lost 6-2).
The largest part of this collection consists of family photos. The majority of these images are taken at Twin Oaks, a mountain retreat. Subjects include bible camps, cook outs, sunsets, and other family activities. These pictures provide fantastic views of the Smoky Mountains. The people included in these photos are family and friends, although it is not clear whether Twin Oaks is owned by one or more families. Other family photos include trips to Stone Mountain in Atlanta, Georgia, a trip to Inverness, Florida, and various holidays and other significant events. There are also historical photos depicting such things as the Sam Houston school near Maryville, Tennessee. Pictures of the Smoky Mountains are taken from Cades Cove, Newfound Gap, and Indian Gap.
Arrangement
Collection consists of two boxes.
Subjects
Great Smoky Mountains (N.C. and Tenn.) -- Pictorial works.; Inverness (Fla.) -- Pictorial works.; Stone Mountain (Ga.) -- Pictorial works.; Tennessee Valley Authority -- Pictorial works.; Tennessee Volunteers (Football team) -- Pictorial works.
Container List
- Twin Oaks, gas tanks and dogwoods, some of Aunt Margaret and Mary Helen, 1955 April 17-19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Twin Oaks, Easter, some of Billy, 1955 March 31-April 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Meyers at Twin Oaks, Mother's Day, The Gafnea's, and Jim Bouman Cabin, 1955 May 1-8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Father's Day and Rev. Caldwell S. S. Clan, 1955 June 21-July 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- River on the Rampage, 2 of Old Cemetery, and Night Blooming Cereus, 1955 July 9-12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Inverness, Florida, Pine Island, and Crystal River, 1955 July 18-31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Atlanta, Georgia, Stone Mountain and Capital, Mary and Charles, 1955 August 5-7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Twin Oaks, Dad painting cabin, Aunt Mable and Uncle Louis, and Pratt Store Fire, 1955 August 13-28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Labor Day, Twin Oaks, and Ramsey Falls, 1955 September 3-5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Family Reunion at Aunt Mable's, Twin Oaks, Vera Pitcher and Mrs. Mackay, 1955 September 25-October 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Pickett State Park, 1955 October 1-1955 October 2 and 1955 October 29-30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Tennessee 7 Georgia Tech 7 also Thanksgiving and Twin Oaks with Lib and Charlie Lynch, 1955 November 6-24 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Christmas Day, Twin Oaks, and Aunt Degies, 1955 December 25-1956 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Norris Dam and Lake, 1956 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Cherokee Dam and Douglas Dam, 1956 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- 5.4 Inches of Snow Around Home, 1956 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Snow, Jeannie Walker, Snow Man, Mrs. Blanketship, 1956 January-February 11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Sonny Frying Steaks and three of our church, 1956 March 9-11 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Chilhowee Dam and Gary Lynch, 1956 February 11-26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Easter, Southern Railway Crash at Powell Station, Cutting Wood at Twin Oaks, 1956 April 1-8 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Dogwood and Twin Oaks, 1956 April 14-24 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Mothers Day and her birthday, playing in the water, Mrs. Brooks and Mrs. Schlank, 1956 May 2-19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Chucky Jack Theater, Mr. and Mrs. Brook and Bill, Francis and Charles Pittman at Twin Oaks, 1956 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Old House, Twin Oaks, Sunsets and Cows, and Circle Number 2 Meeting, 1956 June 9-27 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Rebecca Caldwell Class and Twin Oaks, 1956 June 19-24 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Charlotte Ann Shea, Dan on porch, Sonny and Cookie at Twin Oaks, 1956 July 8-10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Fish Fry and Bill and I, 1956 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Twin Oaks, Ben Jr., and three of Donnie Roland, 1956 August 5-September 3 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Spook Night, Sunday at Hiking Club, 1956 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Cades Cove with Mary and Ann Jones, Tennessee 34 Maryland 7, 1956 October 27-November 4 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Manger and family at our house, 1956 December 17-24 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- New Found Gap and Indian Gap, 39th Wedding Anniversary, 1957 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Fort Loudon Dam and Snow, 1957 February 24-March 8 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Old Sam Houston School and Chilhowee Dam, 1957 March 24 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Young People of the Church at Twin Oaks and Mothers Day, 1957 May 25-June (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Father's Day and Mary and Ann Jones, 1957 June 2-16 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Rebecca Caldwell Bible Class at Twin Oaks, 1957 June 18 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Twin Oaks Birthday Pictures, 1957 July 13- 21 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- The Gafneas and Calberts at Twin Oaks, 1957 July-August 17 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- In Mother's Room at St. Mary's, Rm. 311, good ones of Ann and Mary Jones, 1957 September 15-October 6 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Porch at Twin Oaks, Mountains, Dad, and Sonny cutting down tree, 1957 October 20 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Tennessee 21 Georgia Tech 6 and Trumpet Vine in full bloom, 1957 October 23-November 9 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Cabin in the snow, 1957 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Home, Aunt Mable's, School, and Mary Evelyn House, 1957 December 24-1958 January 30 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Twin Oaks, 1958 February 9 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- The four of us in the living room and Easter Sunday, 1958 February 17-April 6 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Twin Oaks, Mary Catherine Gallaher at Townsend, and the three Mary's, 1958 April 8-1958 April 28 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Wilma, Sonny, Dad, and I taken at Twin Oaks, 1958 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Lunch at Hiking Clubs Cabin, 1958 May 31 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Rebecca Caldwell Bible Class at Twin Oaks, 1958 June 17 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Wedding and Twin Oaks early scenes, 1958 June 20-July 6 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Aunt Mable, Uncle Louie, and Anne at Twin Oaks and Wilma, Sarah, and I in the river, 1958 July 13-27 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- The Fish Fry at Tom DeWine and the Welsh Picnic at Townsend, 1958 August 1-9 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Labor Day at Twin Oaks, 1958 September 1-3 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Frank Parker Cabin, 1958 October 5 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Uncle Don Place, Inverness, Florida, and Films, 1958 October 18-24 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Twin Oaks Spook Night and Tennessee 2 Kentucky 6, 1958 October 25-November 22 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- The Gafneas at Twin Oaks and some of old Same Houston School, and Charles Roth, 1957 March-August (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Welsh Picnic and Twin Oaks and Charles Roth, 1957 August 17-October 20 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Early Pictures, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Prints, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Films, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)